Hello everyone and welcome back
to English pod, my name is Marco.
And my name is Catherine and today
we might just teach you how to save a life.
That's right we're
going to save a life and
we are going to do
this by applying first aid.
So let's take a look at
vocabulary preview and
find out just exactly
what this phrase means.
vocabulary preview.
Okay, so we have this word first aid.
It's two parts.
It is before.
Before.
Early.
And aid.
So when you aid someone
you help them right.
Right.
So this is actually a noun aid is help.
So we're applying first aid.
This means we're the first
person to come and help someone.
So for example, if someone is bleeding,
if the first aid is to stop the bleeding.
Okay.
All right.
So first aid, we're going
to learn all about this.
Take a listen to today's dialogue
and we'll be back in a moment.
Hey Joe, where have you
been these past few days?
I've been busy with
the first aid course that
I started about a week
ago at the Red Cross.
Cool.
I've always wanted to
do something like that.
Have you learnt anything useful?
For sure.
I mean we learned how to
apply pressure to stop bleeding,
how to check for a pulse,
and even how to apply CPR.
Have you treated any real emergencies?
Well, they took us along
with some paramedics.
There was this guy who fell
off his motorcycle and suffered
a concussion as well as a
couple of compound fractures.
His wounds were pretty serious so
they had to rush him to the hospital.
It was intense.
I can imagine.
I tend to faint when I see blood.
So I think I won't be taking up
a course like that anytime soon.
All right.
We're back.
So there are a lot of medical and like
health related terms in this dialogue.
So why don't we take a look at a
couple of those in language takeaway?
Language takeaway.
Well, starting us out here
in language takeaway, we
have the name of an
organization that's not for profit.
That's very, very, very famous.
This is called the Red Cross.
Okay.
So the Red Cross.
Mm-hmm.
And this is usually a place
where you donate blood.
You can also get some blood exams done.
What else do you do there?
Well, the Red Cross is an organization that
has offices and clinics all over the world.
Mm-hmm.
And if you want to help, you can volunteer.
You can donate money
and you can donate blood.
Mm-hmm.
But the Red Cross will take
this and it will help other people.
People who have been in disasters or wars.
Mm-hmm.
And so maybe the Red Cross office near you
will have blood banks and blood donations.
Really, they help people,
they provide aid to people
who are unhealthy or
sick or have been in a war.
A very humanitarian organization.
So worth it.
Go to the Red Cross and donate blood.
In the dialogue, the two people
are discussing real emergencies.
And one person says he went
along with some paramedics.
So a paramedic is a person.
It's a person.
It's a profession, right?
To be a paramedic.
Exactly.
But it's not really a doctor.
So what's the difference here?
So paramedics are something like
nurses, right, that travel in an ambulance
and get to an emergency or get to the
scene of an accident and help out a person.
So they immobilize a
person, they give them oxygen.
They make sure that they stay
alive until they reach the hospital.
Okay, so a paramedic, you
might hear the word medic.
It's the same thing.
A paramedic is like a nurse.
They're not a doctor.
But they're usually
the first person to help
when there's been an
accident or a disaster.
Right, exactly.
So if there is an earthquake and
many people are stuck in the buildings,
usually paramedics will be
the ones on the scene trying
to get them out and helping
them by applying first aid.
Great.
Well, after that, we have finally some of
the injuries that a paramedic might see.
The first injury is usually
associated with the head.
This is called a concussion.
You suffered a concussion.
Sounds painful.
Yeah, it does. And actually,
it's very common, I think, right?
If you fall and you hit your head.
That's right.
So a concussion is really
when your brain hits your skull.
That's the bone that protects your brain.
So really, you're hitting
your head really, really hard.
And usually this can
have some bad side effects.
Like you lose your memory
or you're a little bit confused.
It's very common with football players.
Yeah, yeah.
With any contact support of
people, suffered concussions.
And it's just like imagine when
you have a DVD player and you hit it
and the disc skips or it goes back.
That's kind of what happens to your
brain so you can suffer memory loss.
You can even lose your sight temporarily.
That's right.
So this can be very serious and obviously
should be looked at by a paramedic.
We also have another
situation that is similarly serious.
It's called a compound fracture.
Okay.
So what is a fracture or two fracture?
A fracture is a thing.
It's a break.
Okay, so you could say I broke my arm.
But you could also say I fractured my arm.
This is the more medical term.
But of course there are
different ways to break something.
And so in medicine we
have a compound fracture.
So a compound fracture is pretty
painful and it's a little bit more serious.
You have a simple fracture which
is when your bone just breaks.
Or hairline which means
that there's a little thin part
where it's not, it's broken
but it's not really serious.
In this case your bones
actually push towards each other.
They kind of form like
a little mountain, right?
Or they're on top of each other.
Think about when two cars hit and
they kind of crash up into each other.
Exactly.
It's like that but it's your bone.
So it's extremely painful.
Yeah, yeah, it's very, very painful.
So the person suffered a
concussion and a compound fracture.
Now the friend that he was talking to
said wow, you know, it sounds amazing.
It's really cool that you're doing that.
But you know what?
I faint when I see blood.
Do you do this?
No, I mean either.
Well, some people when they see blood
they feel very, very uncomfortable or sick.
And so to faint is to
fall down on the ground.
It's almost like you're falling asleep.
But it's not sleep.
Have you ever fainted?
I fainted twice in my life.
One time I fainted because of
heat, it was very, very, very hot.
And I couldn't breathe for a moment
and then I woke up on the ground.
Wow.
Yeah.
That's what happens.
Exactly.
So yeah, if you ever
faint, it's basically that
you're just standing there,
you're sitting somewhere
and all of a sudden everything goes black
and you wake up and you're on the ground.
And you feel very, very weak before that.
And very pale, I think as well.
Because your blood
goes away from your brain.
Yeah.
And you pass out.
It's very strange sensation.
Because then everyone else around
you, they know what happened.
They saw you and so they're
looking at you like you're crazy.
Sick.
All right.
So that's too faint.
So those are the key words
that we have for you on language.
Take away.
Let's take a listen to our dialogue again.
And we'll be back shortly to take a
look at some phrases on Fluency Builder.
Hey Joe, where have you
been these past few days?
I've been busy with
the first aid course that
I started about a week
ago at the Red Cross.
Cool.
I've always wanted to
do something like that.
Have you learnt anything useful?
Sure.
I mean, we learned how to apply pressure
to stop bleeding, how to check for a pulse,
and even how to apply CPR.
Have you treated any real emergencies?
Well, they took us along
with some paramedics.
There was this guy who
fell off his motorcycle
and suffered a concussion as well
as a couple of compound fractures.
His wounds were pretty serious, so
they had to rush him to the hospital.
It was intense.
I can imagine.
I tend to faint when I see blood.
So I think I won't be taking up
a course like that anytime soon.
Alright, so quiz, Marco.
What is the first thing
that a paramedic does
when he or she finds a
body at an emergency?
That paramedic checks for a pulse
to make sure you're alive, right?
Right.
A pulse.
The pulse is the rhythm.
It's the sound of your heart pumping blood.
And you can feel someone's
wrist or their throat.
So to check for a pulse means to check
and make sure their heart is pumping blood.
Right.
And not only that, but
to make sure that the
heart is pumping
blood relatively normal.
Because sometimes your heart can
be pumping blood too fast or too slow.
And if it's too slow, it's very
possible that you will faint.
Very good.
Alright, so we check for a pulse.
Now what else happens?
Well, if there's a very
serious emergency and the
paramedic needs help
to give aid to the person
who is injured, then they will
rush that person to the hospital.
Okay.
So the verb to rush.
What does that mean?
Alright.
So to rush someone or
to rush someone to the
hospital means to take someone or
to go with someone very, very quickly.
Okay.
So let's give an example.
I could say, "Listen, Marco, I don't want
to rush you, but I really need the report
done today.
" Or I could say, "I
need to rush home.
My parents need me."
Or if a woman is having a baby, you
want to rush her to the emergency room.
Right.
Okay.
So you need to go quickly.
Alright.
Now we were talking about fainting.
The person said, "Before he used
the word fain, he said, "I tend to faint.
" Okay.
I tend to.
It was a really great verb that
describes a normal or habitual behavior.
That's like saying, "I tend to faint
when it's very, very hot outside.
" That means I often faint
It's something that happens normally.
So it's a tendency.
Right.
But it's not for everyone.
It's for me.
So I tend to.
What's something that you
tend to faint when you see?
I never faint.
You don't faint.
No.
Just kidding.
But you know what?
You tend to leave the towel on the
bed sometimes after I take a shower.
Oh.
I know.
It's a bed.
And then the sheet smell.
No, they don't.
Because I leave it
there for like five or ten
minutes and then I realize
I'm like, "Oh my God.
" And then I pick it up.
But, you know, it's.
It's hard to.
That's gross.
No, it's not.
Well, I tend to forget my leftover
food in the refrigerator for a long time.
Oh, that's even.
And then it starts to smell.
That's gross.
But I don't like to waste food.
But you like let it rot and
then you fridge smells.
That happens.
So, that's all we've got
for fluency builder today.
But we can talk about
tendencies in a moment.
Maybe a homework assignment could be
to think of something that you tend to do.
That's right.
That could be an interesting
homework assignment.
But before we jump
into that, why don't we
listen to our dialogue
for the very last time?
Hey Joe, where have you
been these past few days?
I've been busy with
the first aid course that
I started about a week
ago at the Red Cross.
Cool.
I've always wanted to
do something like that.
Have you learnt anything useful?
For sure.
I mean, we learned how to apply pressure
to stop bleeding, how to check for a pulse,
and even how to apply CPR.
Have you treated any real emergencies?
Well, they took us along
with some paramedics.
There was this guy who fell
off his motorcycle and suffered
a concussion as well as a
couple of compound fractures.
His wounds were pretty serious, so
they had to rush him to the hospital.
It was intense.
I can imagine.
I tend to faint when I
see blood, so I think I
won't be taking up a
course like that anytime soon.
Alright, we're back.
So that's all the time we have for today.
Be sure to do your homework assignment.
Come to EnglishPod.com
in the comments section.
Tell us, what do you tend to do?
Could be a good thing.
Could be a bad thing.
Obviously, you can try and
use some of the vocabulary
you heard in today's lesson
about health and safety.
You might get some extra
points from us for doing that.
I know some people who
tend to leave the house with a
whole medicine kit in
their bags or in their purses.
Really?
We could say a first aid kit.
A first aid kit, exactly.
Wow.
So do you do this?
Let us know.
Our website is EnglishPod.com.
That's all we've got for today.
So until next time.
Bye!
(upbeat music)